I hate to admit it, but one of
my favorite movies is Titanic.
And I love the scene where Mr. Andrews,
after the boat has hit the iceberg,
he's calculating, thinking,
the ship can stay afloat
with four compartments, but
not five, not five breached.
And Ismay's like, but this
ship can't sink. And he's
like, it's made of iron, sir,
it can, and it will. It's
a mathematical certainty.
Well, Mr. Andrews was using
the blueprint for the Titanic.
And the blueprint
represents the instructions,
the guidelines for
putting together the ship.
Similar to blueprints for the
Titanic, we also have blueprints
for homes. And so architects build
very specific instructions for
how to build a home. This happens
to be a blueprint for my home.
And I'm glad we have a blueprint because
on the right-hand side, you can see
we have some high ceilings where I
still don't walk under the chandelier.
I'm afraid it's gonna fall down
one of these days. We also have
rooms with different shapes, and this
is a ceiling in our Christmas room
where you can see the ceiling has 12
different dimensions or corners to
it on the ceiling. And so you'll
become something of an architect
instead of creating blueprints for a
building, you'll then create the
blueprints for designing and creating a
database. And so you'll use ER
diagramming beyond this class. You'll
use it in the engineering program
courses, such as, I think in this case,
data warehousing class. You'll also
use it in the data pipeline class,
and hopefully it's something that
you'll use in your career as well.
At this point, you may want to
pause the video and watch the ER
diagramming video. It's a fairly
comprehensive video on ER diagramming.
It's created by one of your
colleagues, one of our former students,
Gina, and this video, even though
it's 13 years old, is still very
relevant today, covers the topics
that we need, has over a million hits.
And the feedback you
can see is excellent.
Some digs at professors, which are
probably well-deserved. This 15
-minute video is better than a $200
textbook. Remember, you get the
textbook free, I think, online,
or Ben Gaughan is very reasonable.
Three hours of boring university lecture.
That's why this video
supplements the different
talking points that I'll
discuss here in this video.
And then one of my favorites here,
this particular student dropped
out of college, he watched the video,
it completely changed his life.
And now he's no longer in college
debt, making good money all because
of a video. So I don't know if
it'll change your life, but it's
a great video to help complement
the different talking points that
I'll be discussing here today all
right the deliverables for today or
actually for the whole week so for
today we have a blue triad with
this particular video and you can
go to the syllabus for instructions
on the blue triad but effectively
we just want to know that you're
watching the video that you're
following along when you can so for
this particular video you could
upload some notes if you took notes
you could also upload just a few of
the diagrams that we'll create in
Lucidcharts to show that you've
taken time to log in and manipulated
the diagram some. It doesn't have
to be perfect, but just enough
that we know that you've watched
the video. We want you to get credit
for that, and we think that it
will help you on the exams. We also
have a blue triad for a different
video, and then a couple quizzes,
animation, and just a kind of a
topic quiz. As a reminder, those
quizzes are repeatable, and you can
earn up to I guess 100% until you
keep taking it until you earn 100
% and 30 to 40% of those questions
are specifically in the test bank.
Up until this point we've gone
through some database concepts,
principles, terms, table, column, row,
tuple. Tuple rhymes with couple
is the same thing as row. We
traditionally use row now and then a
primary key. So now that you've got
those terms down. In the ER diagramming
world, we also use different
terms. So instead of this being
a table, we call it an entity.
Instead of a column, we now
have an attribute. So if
you think of a student entity,
student has attributes,
last name, first name, just
as a person has attributes,
hair color, height, weight.
So we have attributes
or fields. And then we also
have an entity instance.
Entity instance, you can see
in this case, would be a row.
When we create our ER diagram,
you'll notice we don't have an
entity instance because I'll
explain in just a slide or two. And
then we also have identifiers,
which would be primary keys.
All right, so we're going
to cover the difference in
nomenclature. So the language
of an ER diagram versus just
regular tables, columns,
rows, and how to construct
them. You'll learn a couple
of new terms, relationships,
cardinality, and then how to
represent and place a foreign key in a
one-to-one, one-to-many, or a many
-to-many relationship. So those
are the main topics that we'll
cover today. This happens to be a
sample of an ER diagram. It's a
partial one that we use for class, but
you can see this represents the
blueprint. So in this particular
case, if we're building the data
set, we would know how many entities.
In this case, we would have our
six entities, and within those,
they have different attributes and
identifiers and relationships and
cardinality and and that's what
we'll get into here in a moment
so let's look at some of the terminology
here so as i mentioned before
we have entities now so we have a
student entity and that represents
one theme and everything in in
this er diagram also follows
normalization good normalization
practice we have our attributes that
i mentioned represent what we
referred to before as columns we have
identifiers which would would be
the same thing as a primary key.
We have entity instance,
which shows up here,
but if you look on the
prior slide, you'll
notice there are no entity instances.
There's no data. This represents the
metadata, this represents the blueprint,
but there's no data here.
And so the data doesn't
show up until we build
the tables and start
populating those tables.
And that's the difference between entity
and then an entity instance.
In our next class, our next
video, we will learn about DDL,
creating tables, and DML,
inserting values into tables.
So at this point, you can think
of an entity as where you'll
create the tables based on the
blueprint. And entity instance
is when you start topulating
the tables, and we use something
called DML, data manipulation
language, in order to do that.
And then data types refer to the
type of data, whether it's numeric
or character or date time. data,
and on the left-hand side, these
are the primary data types that
we'll use up through the first exam.
And so in the next video when
we're creating the database
tables,
we have to assign the columns a
data type. And so we're not going
to overcomplicate this. We'll
have either numeric or character
data, or we could have date, time
data to represent a date and time.
So as a brief overview, and we'll
cover this in more detail later,
but we have two types of numeric
data. One is an integer that
we're going to use, and we can use,
as you see on the right-hand side,
you have a tiny integer, which
uses a little bit less space on
the computer, and you have a big
integer, which gives you a lot
more capacity for data. But these
are whole numbers, and they can go
negative or positive, so that
would be an INT integer data type.
If we need a little more
specificity for now,
we're just going to use
numeric data type. And in
that particular case,
we have, as you can see,
numeric four comma two.
And so the four represents,
and I don't know if you'll be
able to see this, but the four
represents four total spaces.
And then the two represents how
many to go back on the decimal. So
this would be four, two. so if
we wanted to have something like
three comma one for numeric we would
go one two three and then we would
just go back one so this would
be three one so the first number
is how many total digits and the
second number is how far to go back
with character data char is
character data meaning they can have
in this case, 30 spaces. So if we
build that, we'll have 30 spaces.
And if we use them, great. If we don't
use them, it still uses 30 spaces.
The varchar, it says varchar 30.
The max could be 30. But if I just
said, Bob, B-O-B, right? B-O-B,
the other 27 spaces aren't used.
And so you think, well, why
wouldn't you use varchar for
everything? Let's get rid of
everything we don't use. Well, Well, it
does take a little more processing
to set up a VARCHAR, and
so a lot of times it works great,
but for instance, if you just
need a two-state acronym each
time, so something like Hawaii,
in this case, you'd be
better to have a CHAR2 than a
VARCHAR because it takes up
more space per character when
you have the VARCHAR. And
then the date time, as you
can see, in this case, it
gives you hours, months, day,
and then years, months, day, and
then hours, minutes, seconds,
and then even milliseconds
in the SQL that we're using.
And we'll use that a little
bit later when we spend an
entire module on dates and times
and those kind of functions.
So that would be a very specific
version of an ERD if you go into the
detail of the data types, but the
more you have, the better. All
right, at this point, let's go
ahead and get into Lucid Charts, and
we'll start to build some of these
ER diagrams or start to model them.
So I'm just going to go under
lucidchart.com, and I'll click that.
And then it's a free login. You'll
be using this for multiple courses.
You may already have one from
2100. I'm not 100% certain on that.
But I've gone ahead and logged
in, and in this case, with
the free login, I'm just
going to click on templates.
then within templates I could scroll
down probably find it I'm just
going to type in ERD and see if
that will find it and so what we'll
be using is the database ER diagram
using crows foot notation and
you can see when you select it
it does provide a template for
you and in this case I think
we'll go ahead and just use the
template to describe it for your
blue triad today if you get logged
in to lucidcharts let's change
just a few of these to represent
some of the ER diagrams
that I showed you earlier,
and that would be great to
upload for the blue tries.
We have a student table
with student ID as the
primary key, last name,
first name, and major.
If we look at that in terms of
normalization, we would indicate
that student ID determines last
name, first name, and major.
And we represent this in an ER
diagram with student being the entity.
student ID is the PK or identifier
and then these represent our columns
or in this particular case our
attributes and we wouldn't have this on
the exam because sometimes it's hard
to tell but you can see that some
of these are bold and one of them is
not bold if they're bold that means
that they are required you have to
put value in and if it's not bold
excuse me if it's not bold you could
leave it, you could leave it null.
So if you have your Lucid charts on
the screen, as I mentioned earlier,
we do have a template that Lucid
has provided, kind of just set
up a sample ER diagram. You could
go over to the Entity Relationship
information that they have here
and pull over a new entity as well.
It just doesn't have all the fancy
components built into it quite
yet. But let's go ahead and use the
sample one if they have that one.
If they don't, then, excuse me,
if they don't, you could drag one
over from your entity relationship
and build that. But this
particular one, let's go ahead and
build the entity, call it student.
And then in this case, we would
have a maybe a student ID.
And a student ID key in this
case would likely be that integer
data type, and it would also
represent the primary key for
this table. So in this particular
attribute, the way that
it's set up is the detail level
doesn't include identifiers,
at least by, you know,
built in to the entity.
I guess you could put
PK here or something.
But if you right click on your entity,
you do have, or I guess if you
just click on the entity, you
have an option to change that
entity to have more detail or
less detail. So here I can
click on Entity Key Field Type
and that gives a little more
detail possibility in this case
indicating either a primary key
or no primary key. We've made
a student entity with student
ID being the primary key and
we can continue to fill this out
so could have a last name and
that would likely be a chart
say 30 data type so if you would
go ahead and fill in yours as far
as your blue triad in interest
of time I'm going to skip over
to this one and in this case
we'll create let's just create
the gym locker I think of the arc
In fact, I won't put the underscore,
it's probably not a good idea,
even though I think we have it in
ours. We have a gym locker. Here
we might have the locker ID, and
this would be an integer data type.
And then that would represent
kind of the basics of the
entities, the attributes, the
data types, and the identifier.
Now let's figure out these
lines. We've got these lines
and then what are referred to
as the crow's foot notation.
Great. So let's tackle relationship.
So relationship is just
a connection between two
tables to indicate that
there is a relationship.
So in this case we have a line
and the lines happen to have
arrows to show a relationship
between these two tables.
And then you can see with the
relationship we also have some verbs.
Now this is getting to be overkill.
Usually one verb is the most, but if
you do have two verbs, if you want
to go for it, you have two verbs,
you would read from left to right.
So you would say a student has a
phone, in this case, or a phone,
starting with this table or entity, a
phone is assigned to a student. So
you would read the item closest to
the table. So a student has a phone
or a phone is assigned to a student.
Typically you just have one word.
Student has, if you want to create
the verb to describe that relationship
now relationship does refer
to a degree and for this particular
class when you think of degree it
just means how many how many
relationships are we discussing in this
case you can see a student is is
linked to the phone so this is a binary
relationship almost every relationship
we'll use in 5300 is a binary
relationship so this table to this
table. Now it is possible to have
what's called a unary relationship.
I think I have a slide later where
a table or entity refers to itself.
I'll describe that in a bit. Or
we could have a ternary where we
have three tables that are related.
But the link to those is not from
one table to another. We would have
kind of an intersection of these
lines. But for what we're doing in
class, everything will be a binary
relationship. If there's a question
on the exam, what's the most
common degree the degree common is
always or the common degree is always
going to be a binary relationship
so let's pull the ER diagram over
and we have a student and a gym
locker table and now at this point
we just have the relationship we'll
worry about these other lines later
these little that little single
line and the little crow's foot
looks like kind of a witch's broom or
something but at this point we
have the relationship between these
two tables and if you simply double
click on the relationship line it
does give you an opportunity and in
this case any kind of verb is fine
just so you can say a student has a
gym locker or a student is assigned
a gym locker and you can include
two if you wanted to but this
is the relationship showing a binary
relationship binary because the
line refers to two tables or two
entities in this particular case and
that would lead us to these lines
here which represent our cardinality.
And here is a sample of cardinality
through crow's foot notation.
And so you do have the opportunity
to describe your table into
more detail. So cardinality
represents how many or how few,
what's the minimum, what's
the maximum allowed with
this relationship. For
instance, with our, well, let me
bring it over, with ours,
we have a couple of choices,
we can say one gym locker
can belong to many students.
That's the way that
it's set up right now.
And that would be cardinality one
to many. And that is what we're
describing here when I go back to this
chart. So the options that we have are
zero to one. So a student could have
no gym lockers or one gym locker.
That's how you could indicate it.
They're not required to participate
but they could they can only do one
activity you can have a one and only
one meaning you're required to have
a lot so high school you're required
to have a locker and each person
has their own locker the other
options are you're not required to
have a locker or participate but if you
do you could have many lockers or in
this case you have to have a locker
but you could also have many
lockers so those are kind of the
possibilities for cardinality so in
this case the way I think I have it set
up in our diagram is a student, one
student can have one gym locker. That's
just how we set it up. So then we
just have to find the lines, and
those lines, at least in Lucid charts,
are found up here, where in this
case we're probably looking for one
and only one student can have one.
Now
the difference between these
two, this just provides more
detail. This would say one and
only one student it just says
one student so we probably
will go ahead and make those
oops excuse me let me click on
this and we probably we would make
those the same so in this case we're
saying one and only one student
has one and only one gym locker and
what this would indicate is that
the gym locker in this case is
required you have to have a gym locker
If you didn't want to have a gym locker
required, then you could
change it to 0 to 1.
So a student can have 0 to 1 gym lockers.
And I'm assuming you'll fill
this in for the blue triad.
And then the other option is,
well, you could have one to many.
So in this case, you're required
to one, but you could have many.
How many can you have?
and there's a famous kind of database
feature. How many can you have? Many.
So in this case, you would
indicate many. There may be a
number or something close to
it to indicate the maximum,
but the notion is just
unlimited unless if you
specify a value there. So
in a course or a gym locker,
maybe the maximum would be
two or three, but you would
indicate that. And then when
we build the database, there's
specificity as how we
would do that. So these are
kind of the basics of the ER
diagram. We have the entity.
We have the entity name. We have the
attributes. We have the data types.
We also indicate if they
are primary key or not.
So here we can call this a PK or a key.
And we'll indicate that.
We have a relationship
between these two tables.
That's a binary relationship.
and in this case one and only
one student can have one too
many lockers is how we have
this particular ER diagram set
up. This is about all you would
need to submit for your blue
triad for this to show that
you've been following along.
Now let's take a look at
the final piece for this
particular video is how do
we implement the foreign key.
Let me bring the ER diagram. We
do have one more thing to indicate
here if we want that specificity
is where are we going to place the
foreign key and right now we have
let's go back to where we had it
before we had a one-to-one one
mandatory so now the question is where
do we place the foreign key how
do we link these two tables back
up here are options we can either
take student ID from the student
table and put it in the locker ID
table or we can take the locker ID
and put it in the student ID or
student table. Those are our two
options. So the question here is,
where do we place the foreign key?
On a one-to-one implementation,
so here we have it,
one-to-one, just as we
have in Lucid chart. The
answer is, it doesn't matter.
It will work either way.
How you would then approach
is, which table do you consider
to be the parent, and which do
you consider to be the child?
In this particular case, I would
consider the student table to be more
valuable at a university than a locker
table, and in this case, I would
put the SID, student ID, I would
put it over here, and I would call
this, in this case, I would put FK,
and now I would change this to PK,
where before it didn't matter. Now, if
you want to add fields,
you can add fields
through the menu item. You just
click on it and add fields,
but this is how I would set
up Let's go back to two,
oops, four, three, two.
This is how, at a minimum,
you would set it up,
and that would be in a
one-to-one relationship.
Now, we can look at some
other possibilities.
We have the one-to-one.
If you had a one-to-many, where
do you place the foreign key?
And in a one-to-many, you always place
the foreign key on the many side.
So in this case, you don't have a
choice. you have to put the student
ID on the one side the parent
side into the child side and the
reason for that is on the mini side
if you think about this you have
a phone number I have a phone
number 555 this is me and it's my
home number and then I have a phone
number 444 it's still me and so
I can show up here many times and
that could be my cell number my
work number my I don't have a guest
cabin or something but if i had
a cabin or a beach house or
something but the point is that's why
the foreign key has to be on the
mini side so you don't have a choice
like the one-to-one because in the
one-to-one you're only you're only
going to have one max entered there
and then the most important one is
on a many-to-many relationship how
is that handled in an er diagram
you most certainly could have something
that looked like this a mini-to
-many so an activity and a student,
and then we have this bridge table.
And here's the problem, and here's
what we would originally have. A
student can participate in many
activities. Stick with me here. An
activity can have many students, so
we have a many-to-many relationship.
If we look at that and we put the
foreign key here, student ID and
activity, don't think of this. Don't
think of the bottom one. If we do
that, then we can only have one
student participate in an activity.
And if we move activity ID over
to the student table, then that
student can only, because these are
always one, one student ID, one last
name, one first name. So you can
only have one activity ID, one
activity the student can participate
in. So that's why a many-to-many,
and you'd see it in the video if
you watched that as the follow
-up, it doesn't work. So for all
many-to-many, the answer is you have
to create a bridge or an association
table and create two one-to
-many's. Now, the nice thing is if
you don't know what to call it, you
simply call it the name of the
first table, underscore the name of
the second table, and they both, the
primary keys are both the primary
key and the foreign key. And in
that case, a student can participate
in many activities, and an
activity can contain many students.
So let's do some review
with our final diagram and
take a look at some of these
relationships cardinality.
In this case, we have the
student table and the gym
locker table, and they do have
a one-to-one relationship.
We don't have any verbs
listed here, but okay, that's
still as detailed as we
thought we needed to be.
So here we have a gym locker and a
student table. We have the student ID.
We have the locker ID, so we
know we're going to have to put
one of these into the other
table. So we can either put the
locker ID in the student table
or the student ID into the
locker table. We place the
foreign key. In this case, I would
recommend either. So on the
exam, if you said either, that's
the correct answer if you
decided. So it doesn't matter.
But in this case, you'd put
it in the less important
one, perhaps. So you'd
put student ID here.
Then we also have a situation where
a student can have many awards,
and an award can be
given to many students.
And see, remember, that's a many
-to-many relationship, and it's
not allowed. the giveaway here
is look at the name of this table
student award so we have student
underscore award this is the link
between that many-to-many
otherwise as a reminder we can only
have one student ID in the award
table so that means an award could
only ever go to one student or
if we put the award ID in the
student table that means the award
could only go to one student so
to do to overcome that we create
the one-to-many the primary keys
of each table become the primary
and foreign key. So one-to-one,
it doesn't matter. One-to-many,
you place it in the child table,
and many-to-many, you would
create that bridge or association
table. And then as a reminder
on the degree relationship,
binary relationship is the
most common. The only other one
that we will use a little bit
later is a unary relationship.
And don't overthink this,
but look at this, this table,
the key, primary key to
many, a one to many, has a
relationship with itself.
This is a unary relationship.
The idea would be, in
this case, you can see we
have an employee ID, and
they have some managers,
a manager. So each employee has a
manager, except for the top employee,
like the CEO, they don't have,
they wouldn't have a manager under
them. But all the rest of them would.
So if this was null, you would know
that they're either not assigned
or they're the CEO but in this case
if you think of the characteristics
of the employee so last name first
name city state then you think of
the characteristics of a manager they
would be the same last name city
first name state gender and the idea
of a unary relationship is not to
have to repeat an entire table just
to add one attribute and so
effectively this unary relationship can
link up the employee ID to the
manager ID so effectively when When we
join these, we could see all of the
information about the employee and
all of the information about the
manager by joining to a single table.
And again, we'll do that a little
bit later in the semester. And
that concludes the ER diagramming.
This is just looking forward to the
next video where we'll start to
use those ER diagrams to create
what are called the DDL, data
definition language, and then ultimately
the DML to populate those data
sets. We'll start that video next.
Thank you. Have a good day.